Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY, 151 documents (irregularly numbered 1-133)
  - Relazione della Seconda Battaglia nell'acque di Corfu. Ms. in Italian. 1 page (f. 304). Report on the second sea battle at Corfu. (Box 62, Folder 107)
  - Melazzo, 5 Octobre (1718). Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 305-306. Report on the operations of the English fleet under the command of Admiral Bing in the waters of Corfu. (Box 62, Folder 108)
  - Messina, li 24 Luglio 1718. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 307-308. Report on ship movements around Sicily. (Box 62, Folder 109)
  - Reggio, 10 Ottobre 1718. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 309-310. On naval engagements. (Box 62, Folder 110)
  - Acquaviva, Cardinal. Billet sent to Cardinal Giudice, dated Jan. 6, 1718. With Giudice's answer. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages (f. 311). (Box 62, Folder 111)
  - Lede, Marchese di. Copia di Lettera scritta...al Signor Marchese di Montemar. Printed leaflet. 9 pages, numbered ff. 313-317. Palermo, F. Cichè, 1719. Letter on the victory. (Box 62, Folder 112)
  - Relazione Distinta...delle solenne Entrata in Vienna delle Grande Ambasciata Ottomana...14 di Agosto 1719. Printed news supplement sheet. 2 pages (f. 318). (Box 62, Folder 113)
  - Charles VI, Emperor. Printed announcement. 3 pages, numbered ff. 319-320. Napoli, 1719. (Box 62, Folder 114)
  - June 24, 1719. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 321-322. Report on the battles fought between Spaniards and Germans in the waters off Messina. (Box 62, Folder 115)
  - Vienna, 29 Aprile 1719. Printed extra sheet to an Italian newspaper. 2 pages (f. 323). On the Imperial legation to the Turks. (Box 62, Folder 116)
  - Distinto Ragguaglio della solenne Udienza...4 Settembre 1719. Description of the meeting between Emperor Charles VI and the Turkish Ambassador. Printed extra sheet to an Italian newspaper. 4 pages, numbered ff. 324-325. (Box 62, Folder 117)
  - Relazione del ingresso solenne...3 Agosto 1719 in Constantinopili. Entry of the Italian ambassador into Constantinople. Printed extra sheet to an Italian newspaper. 2 pages (f. 326). (Box 62, Folder 118)
  - June 24, 1719. Another ms. copy of item 115. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 327-328. (Box 62, Folder 119)
  - Journals 1726-1727. Ms. in Italian. 22 pages, numbered ff. 329-339. Diary notes on current events. (Box 62, Folder 120)
  - Ancona, 5 Agosto 1733. Printed news sheet (no. 33 of an Italian newspaper). 4 pages, numbered ff. 340-341. With international news events. (Box 62, Folder 121)
  - Manifeste de la Republique de Bologne approuvé dans le Champ Electoral entre Varsovie et Wola. Printed leaflet in French and Italian in two columns. 4 pages, numbered ff. 342-343. Dated Sept. 4, 1733. (Box 62, Folder 122)
  - Capitula di Carta del Conde de Montemar... Printed pamphlet in Spanish and Italian in two columns. 6 pages, numbered ff. 344-346. Letter from Count Montemar to Monsignor Ratto, Bishop of Cordova, May 27, 1734. With a duplicate, ff. 361-363. (Box 62, Folder 123)
  - Napoli, 26 Marzo 1734. Ms. in Italian. 5 pages, numbered ff. 349-351. An address by the Neapolitans to the Emperor. (Box 62, Folder 124)
  - Ancona, 22 Sept. 1734. Printed news sheet. 2 pages (f. 352). (Box 62, Folder 125)
  - Don Carlos. Don Carlos por la Gracia de Dios... Printed proclamation in Spanish and Italian in 2 columns. 1 page, folio, folded (f. 353). Dated March 14, 1734. (Box 62, Folder 126)
  - Don Carlos por la Gracia de Dios, Infante de Castilla... Ms. in Spanish. 3 pages (f. 354). Don Carlos appointing Manuel de Orleans, Count of Charney to the Naples Government. Dated April 13, 1734. (Box 62, Folder 127)
  - Bologna, Li 19 Ottobre 1734. Printed newspaper (no. XLII). 4 pages, numbered ff. 356-357. (Box 62, Folder 128)
  - Conde de Clavigo. Ms. in Spanish. 1 page (f. 358). Copy of a proclamation, dated Naples, March 24, 1734. (Box 62, Folder 129)
  - Copie d'une Lettre de M. le Marechal de Coigny. Printed leaflet with French and Italian in two columns. 3 pages, numbered ff. 359-360. Dated Parma, June 30, 1734. (Box 62, Folder 130)
  - Regimen y Disciplina que deven observar Los Regimentos de Cavalleria y Dragones Que Serven en este Estado de Milan. Printed leaflet in Spanish. 11 pages, numbered ff. 365-370. Undated (1735). (Box 62, Folder 131)
  - Ancona, November 16, 1735. Printed news sheet in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 371-372. With international news. (Box 62, Folder 132)
  - Napoli, December 1736. Ms. in Italian. 1 page (f. 373). News about a victory of the Spaniards over an Algerian fleet. (Box 62, Folder 133)
- RELATIONE DI CONCLAVE
  - Manuscript in Italian. 569 pages and 703 pages. Bound in 2 volumes. Folio. Contemporary brown morocco, vellum backs. Italy, 17th century. (Box 63.1)
  - Relatione di Conclave. Accounts of the conclaves from the election of Clement V in 1305 up to the election of Innocent X in 1644. The first volume leads from Clement V to Gregory XIV (1591); the second volume from Innocent IX (1591) to Innocent X (1644), the latter being the most comprehensive account. (Box 63.2)
- HISTORIES
  Three manuscripts, comprising 630 pages. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - Tassoni, Alessandro. Annali Ecclesiastici, Volume Primo. Ms. in Italian. 557 pages, numbered ff. 1- 279. Tassoni (1565-1635), best known as the inventor of the "mock-heroic poem," writes here an ecclesiastical history, based on the famous Annales Ecclesiastici by Cardinal Baronius. The first volume of Tassoni's abrégé leads up to the year 226. (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Gualterio, Guido. Sixti V Pontificis Optimi Maximi Ephemerides. Ms. in Latin. 333 pages, numbered ff. 280-447. Detailed annals of the Papacy of Sixtus V (1585-1590). (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Relatione della Dieta di Polonia et Elettione in Re dil Sig. Duca Michaele Wiszniewiecki. Ms. in Italian. 18 pages, numbered ff. 449-458. Account of Poland and the elecion of Muchael Korbut Wiszniewiecki to the Polish throne in 1669. (Box 64, Folder 3)
- MISCELLANY, 18 manuscript documents, comprising 477 pages.
  Folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, 18th century.
  - Strozzi, Lorenzo. Vita di Filippo Strozzi di Fiorenze. Ms. in Italian. 85 pages, numbered ff. 1-43. The life of Filippo Strozzi (1488-1538) by his brother Lorenzo. This biography was printed in the 1727 edition of Varchi's Storia Fiorentina. (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Regolamente di Vita Civile per una Dama Giovane. Ms. in Italian. 36 pages, numbered ff. 45-62. Advice and maxims of behavior in social life for a young lady, by an unknown author of the early 18th century. (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Relazione de Tumulti accaduti in Roma l'Anno 1736, loro origine e sequele. Ms. in Italian. 77 pages, numbered ff. 63-101. Refers to the political opposition in Rome against Spain in the year 1736. (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Maghetti, Geronimo. Per l'Armamente del Anno 1744. Ms. in Italian. 23 pages, numbered ff. 102-113. Memoir to Pope Benedict XIV with suggestions for improvements in the recruitment and organization of the Papal army. (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - La Predica della Carita Pelosa. Ms. in Italian. 17 pages, numbered ff. 114-122. A satirical sermon showing how charity may turn from a virtue into a sin. (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Donazione di Constantio alla Chiesa, se sia stata reale o pur sognata. Ms. in Italian. 6 pages, numbered ff. 123-125. An essay on the Donation of Constantine, proving it to have been an historical event, not a legend. Undated. (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Scrittura Lasciata nelle mani del Sig. Francesco Maria Saoli... Ms. in Italian. 6 pages, numbered ff. 127-129. Paoli was the head of the delegation sent to negotiate with General Selané, commander of the French troops sent by Louis XIV against Genoa, after the Genoese had placed themselves under Spain's protection. (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Louis XIV and the Turks. Lettera scritta del Gran Turco al Re Christianissimo. Copy of a letter by Mahomet to Louis XIV and the French King's answer, dated Paris, July 9, 1669. Also with the oath (in Latin) by Francis I, King of France, testifying to his desire to remain on good terms with Soliman of Turkey and the latter's promise of friendship. Ms. in Italian. 9 pages, numbered ff. 131-135. (Box 65, Folder 8)
  - Vita, Profezie, Morte, e Miracoli del Beato Bartolomeo Carosi, alias detto Brandano il Pazzo di Gesu Cristo della Citta di Siena. Ms. in Italian and Latin. 64 pages, numbered ff. 136-167. Contains a biography of Carosi (1483-c. 1550) in Italian and his prophesies in Latin. (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Vita di Tiberio Fiorelli, Sopra nominato Scaramuccia, Famosissimo Comico et Istrione del Suo Tempo, e Gracioso Buffone. Ms. in Italian. 94 pages, numbered ff. 168-214. A life of the famous Italian comic actor of the 17th century, who created the stock character of Italian comedy, "Scaramouche." (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - Lettera del Gran Turco all'Imperator Leopold Primo L'Anno 1701. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 215-216. Copy of a letter by Mustafa II, Sultan of Turkey, to Leopold I, dated Constantinople, 1701. (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Copia di Lettera dell'Imperatore della Cina a Papa Clemente XI... Ms. in Italian. 5 pages, numbered ff. 216-218. Copy of a letter of the Emperor of China to Pope Clement XI, translated by a Jesuit. Dated 1706. (Box 65, Folder 12)
  - Regalo mandato dall'Imperatore della Cina al Papa. Ms. in Italian. 1 page (f. 219). Sequel to the above (no. 12). (Box 65, Folder 13)
  - Lettera d'Alfonso Secondo, Re di Napoli. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages (f. 220). Dated Rome, 1667. (Box 65, Folder 14)
  - Ridicolosita degli Ebrei Del Talmut. Ms. in Italian. 12 pages, numbered ff. 221-226. An essay, ridiculing the Jews and the Talmud. Undated. (Box 65, Folder 15)
  - Ridicolosita de Turchi. Ms. in Italian. 19 pages, numbered ff. 227-236. Essay ridiculing the Turks and the Qu'ran. Undated. (Box 65, Folder 16)
  - Difference des Cinq Nations. Ms. in French. 4 pages, numbered ff. 237-238. Characterization of the national traits of the Germans, the English, the French, the Italians, and the Spanish. Undated. (Box 65, Folder 17)
  - Relazione della morte che fece il Principino Savelli... Ms. in Italian. 14 pages, numbered ff. 239-245. Account of the murder of the young prince Savelli by a rival, under the Papacy of Paul III (1534-1549). (Box 65, Folder 18)
- VITE DI HUOMINI...
  Vite di Huomini, et Donne Illustri di Filetimo Alicarnasseo. 8 biographical sketches, with an introduction. Dived into two books, the first comprising Items 1-5; the second Items 6-8. ff. 1-212. Small folio. Contemporary vellum; uncut. Italy, n.d.
  - Avolos, Dorotea d', Duchess of Francavilla. Vita della Principessa di Francavilla. Laudatory biographical sketch, undated. Dorotea d'Avalos was apparently a sister of Inigo d'Avalos (d. 1503). 15 leaves, numbered ff. 3-17. Preceded by an introduction to the volume, ff. 1-3. In Italian. (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Colonna, Prospero. Vita di Prospero Colonna. Laudatory biographical sketch of Prospero Colonna, son of Antonio Colonna and an Italian captain, who died in 1523. 14 leaves, numbered ff. 18-32. In Italian. (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Isabella of Aragon, Duchess of Milan. Vita di Donna Isabella d'Aragona, Duchesa di Milano. Biographical sketch, with introductory sketch of Petrarcha. Isabella, daughter of King Ferdinand II of Naples, married to Gean Galeazzo Sforza, Duke of Milan. Isabella became Duchess of Bari in 1500, and died in 1524. 11 leaves, numbered ff. 32-43. In Italian. (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Avalos, Ferdinando Francesco d', Marquis of Pescara. Vita di D. Ferrando Francesco d'Avalos Marchese di Pescara. Undated. Biographical sketch. The Marquis of Pescara, born in Naples in 1490, was married to Vittoria Colonna, and died from wounds received at the Battle of Pavia, in 1525. 15 leaves, numbered ff. 44-58. In Italian. (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Colonna, Vittoria, Marchioness of Pescara. Vita d'Vittoria Colonna, Marchese di Piscara. Undated. Biographical sketch. Vittoria (1490-1547) married Ferdinando Francesco d'Avalos, Duke of Pescara in 1507, being widowed in 1525. She is known for her poetry and for being loved by Michelangelo when she was 35 years old. 16 leaves, numbered ff. 60-75 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Avalos, Alfonso d', Marquis del Vasto. Vita di D. Alfonso d'Avalos d'Aquino, Marchese del Vasto. Undated. Biographical sketch in Italian. The Marquis of Vasto (d. 1546) distinguished himself in the battles of Italy, and against the Turks, under Charles V. He was a son of Inigo d'Avalos, Marquis of Vasto. 68 leaves, numbered ff. 76-144. (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Maria of Aragon, Marchioness of Vasto. Vita di D. Maria d'Aragona Marchesa del Vasto. Undated. Biographical sketch in Italian. 34 leaves, numbered ff. 145-179. (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Pedro de Toledo, Marquis of Villafranca, Viceroy of Naples. Vita di D. Pietro di Toledo V.R. di Nap. Undated. Biographical sketch in Italian. Pedro de Toledo (1484-1553), warrior and governor of Naples. 33 leaves, numbered ff. 179-212. (Box 66, Folder 8)
- REPUBLIC OF PISA
  - History of the Pisans. 132 numbered leaves. With full-page pen and water color drawing of a coat of arms, with inscription "Bened(ictu)s Ludovici Vitalis obdecus Carr()s N." 8vo. Contemporary vellum. N.pl., n.d. (17th century). (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - A history of the Republic of Pisa from the time around the year 1000 AD to October 8, 1406 when the Republic of Florence occupied Pisa.
  - Annexed is a list of the major buildings in the city of Pisa, including their measurements, followed by facts concerning Church government of the Republic.
- MARRETTI, LELIO. RICCORDI POLITICI
  - Lelio Marretti, Riccordi Politici. Manuscript in 2 parts. Together 1608 pages, numbered ff. 1-401 and ff. 1-403. Folio. 2 vols. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, 17th century. (Box 68.1)
  - This comprehensive work on politics, written in accordance with the rules of Tacitus, Livius, and other historians of antiquity, is divided into two parts: La Politica Civilie and La Politica Economica. (Box 68.2)
  - The author, Lelio Marretti from Siena, was active in the late 16th and early 17th centuries. He was an erudite gentleman who served as consultant in affairs of the state and in legal matters to several princes and cardinals and was well versed in the policies and laws of the court of Rome. He was the author of several works on political science, none of them published, of which Azzolini said (in 1649) were "an arsenal of wisdom and admired by everyone who had the good fortune to read them."
  - The work is present here in a manuscript copy, written in three or four 17th century hands.
  - See Azzolini, Le Pompe Sanesi, (1649), II, pp. 41-42.
- BARBETTA DA SINIGAGLIA, C. IL PLETTRO DELLE MUSE
  - Ms. in Italian. 266 pages, numbered ff. 1-133. Italy, n.d. (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Barbetta da Sinigaglia, C. Il Plettro delle Muse. This volume contains a collection of Italian poems by Carlo Barbetta da Sinigaglia, a minor poet of the 17th century, unmentioned in the standard works on 17th century literature (Belloni, Pompeati, etc.).
- ASSORTED NEWS ITEMS, 1689-1732, 95 manuscripts, 382 pages; and 54 printed news items
  320 pages; together, 702 pages. Thick 8vo. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, 18th century.
  - Colonia, 20 Marzo, 1689. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 2-3. A report on military events in Germany during the war of 1689, when Louis XIV invaded and devastated Germany, whose Emperor at that time was Leopold I. (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - A letter by a Sig. Nardi, dated Oct. 26, 1694. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages (f. 4). (Box 71, Folder 2)
  - Rome, 20 April, 1701. Political news report. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages, numbered ff. 5-8. (Box 71, Folder 3)
  - Rome, July 13, 1701. News report. Ms. in Italian. 7 pages, numbered ff. 9-12. (Box 71, Folder 4)
  - Rome, October 21, 1702. News report. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 15 and 16 (skipping a printed pamphlet). (Box 71, Folder 5)
  - Copia d'Una Lettera scritta Dal Marescial di Villars al Re Christianissimo...a'19 di Febbrajo (1703). Printed in Italian. 6 pages. (Box 71, Folder 6)
  - Manifesto del Duca Moles... Imbasciador di Carlo II, Re di Spagna, alla Corte Cesarea. Printed in Italian. 15 pages. Vienna, March 19, 1703. (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - Vienna, 15 Sept. 1703. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages. A report giving information about the ceremonies accompanying the appointment made by Emperor Leopold I of Austria of his son Charles III to the Kingship of Spain. (Box 71, Folder 8)
  - Warsaw, August, 1703. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages. A report concerning military events of 1703, which marked the entire occupation of Poland by the Swedes under Charles XII, after the Battle of Clissow. (Box 71, Folder 9)
  - Mellarede, Monsieur de, Ambassadeur de S.A.R. le Duc de Savoye au Mémoire de...Marquis de Puysieux... 7 November 1703. Printed in French. 3 pages (skipping a leaflet). (Box 71, Folder 10)
  - Venezia, 13 June, 1703. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages, numbered ff. 17-20. A report concerning the international events of 1703. "If the King of Sweeden fails to decide to give peace to Poland, Venice will declare war against him." (Box 71, Folder 11)
  - Relacion de la Victoire...près du Danube. Aug. 13, 1704. Printed. 2 pages. In French. (Box 71, Folder 12)
  - Lettre de...Baron de Hompesch... Printed in French. 2 pages. Dated Hoghster, Aug. 13, 1704. Clipping. (Box 71, Folder 13)
  - Hesse-Cassel, Fredrich, Prince of. Lettre...a leurs Siegneurs, Les Etats Generaux. Printed 1 page (Clipping). Dated Aug. 13, 1704. (Box 71, Folder 14)
  - Nouvelles Extraordinaire. Printed in French. Clipping, 1 column. (Box 71, Folder 15)
  - Marlborough, Duc de. Letter. August 14, 1704. Printed in French. 1 column. (Box 71, Folder 16)
  - Chara Deo Pietas ey vero Consona Vera. Printed. 3 pages. Report and extract of a letter by Principe Eugenio to the Count of Lamberg, Imperial Ambassador in Rome. August 22, 1704. (Box 71, Folder 17)
  - Capitulazione della Città...di Milano. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, dated Sept. 24, 1706. A copy of the Document of Surrender of the City and Duchy of Milan, on the part of the Duke of Savoy (and of Count Gian Battista Scotti and Alberto Stampa) to the Emperor of Austria. The Duke of Savoy and Counts profess their loyalty to the Emperor and place themselves under his protection. (Box 71, Folder 18)
  - Gaceta de Madrid. Printed in Spanish. Together 12 pages. News items. (Box 71, Folder 19-21)
  - Grimani, Sig. Card. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 21 and 24. Dated Rome, Feb. 12, 1707. (Box 71, Folder 22)
  - Levito, Augustin. A copy of a speech delivered by Don Augustin Levito to the King of Sweeden in Poland, by order of the Pope. Ms. in French. 4 pages. Dated Berlin, November 8, 1707. Some news items follow. (Box 71, Folder 23)
  - Ascoli, Sig. d' Lettera d'un Gentiluomo d'Ascoli ad un Ministro di Napoli. Printed in Italian. 27 pages. The last letter is dated Barcelona, August 14, 1707. (Box 71, Folder 24)
  - Napoli, November 8, 1707. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages. Business matters and news. (Box 71, Folder 25)
  - Napoli, Nov. 8, 1707. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. (Box 71, Folder 26)
  - July 28, 1708. Ms. 1 page, numbered f. 29. (Box 71, Folder 27)
  - July 29, 1708. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 30-31. In Italian. Report from a policeman or secret agent concerning the activities of a certain Colonel Don Antonio Caraccioli. Dated July 19, 1708. (Box 71, Folder 28)
  - Report. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages. (Box 71, Folder 29)
  - Report about the defeat of the French Army in its attempt to cross the river at Oudenarde, Belgium. The Battle of Oudenarde is famous as a great victory gained by Marlborough and Eugene over the French under Vendome. It took place on July 11, 1708. Datelined July 12, 1708. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 33 and 36. (Box 71, Folder 30)
  - Lettera scritta dall'...Grimani. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 34-35v. A letter by Grimani to Podiucci, Papal Secretary of State, concerning political claims of the Holy See. Dated June 29, 1708. (Box 71, Folder 31)
  - A letter, unsigned, dated April 29, 1708. Concerning political and military matters (war, refusal of Pope to quarter German troops, danger of Neapolitan invasion of Papal States, etc.). Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, numbered f. 38. 4to., folded. (Box 71, Folder 32)
  - Letter dated Aug. 4, 1708. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, 4to, numbered ff. 39r and v. (Box 71, Folder 33)
  - Boletino...1708. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 40-41. News bulletin about the events of the War of 1708. (Box 71, Folder 34)
  - Boletino...1708. Ms. in Italian. 21 pages, numbered ff. 44-55. More news bulletins about military events of 1708, sent to Baron Carlo D'Asti in Rome. (Box 71, Folder 35)
  - 13 News bulletins of the same kind in forms of letters. Ms. in Italian. 22 pages, numbered ff. 58- 80. From the years 1708 and 1709. (Box 71, Folder 36)
  - Milano, 22 Settembre 1709. Printed news bulletin. 4 pages. Milan, 1709. (Box 71, Folder 37)
  - Bull. Barcelona, 1709. Ms. in Italian. 1 page, numbered f. 81. (Box 71, Folder 38)
  - Barcelona, 25 Agosto 1720. Ms. in Italian. 1 page, numbered f. 82. A news bulletin, announcing the victory gained by the army of the King of Spain. (Box 71, Folder 39)
  - Lione, 25 Nov. 1712. Ms. in Italian. 1 page, numbered f. 83. A diplomatic dispatch from Lyons, unsigned and dated, announcing that peace will be proclaimed at the end of the fall. The peace between England and France was signed in 1713 (Utrecht). (Box 71, Folder 40)
  - Discorso di Sua Ecc...Don Lorenzo Verzuso Beretti Landi... della Maesta Filippo Quinto... Printed in Italian. 4 pages. (Box 71, Folder 41)
  - Supplemento. Ms. in Italian. 16 pages, numbered ff. 84-91. News items and rumors from Rome, relative to the year 1713. (Box 71, Folder 42)
  - Discours de son Excell...Marquis de Chatreauneuf... Printed in French. 1 page. Dated Jan. 18, 1714. (Box 71, Folder 43)
  - Sacrae Vaesarae Majestatis Caroli Sexti. Ms. in Latin. 2 pages, numbered ff. 92r & v. Dated Feb. 8, 1714. Official decree by Charles VI, German Emperor, expelling the diplomatic representatives of the Kingdom of Piedmont-Savoy (in particular, Ambassador Provana) from the territories of Germany. (Box 71, Folder 44)
  - Articoli di Pace conclusi in Rastat...March 7, 1714. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, numbered f. 93. Articles of the Peace of Rastadt which set an end to the War of the Spanish Succession. The peace between Austria and France was signed on March 7, 1714, between Prince Eugene (for Austria) and Marshal Villars, for France. (Box 71, Folder 45)
  - Nouvelles Extraordinaires de Divers Endroits...27 March 1714. 5 various news letters, printed in various languages. ca. 34 pages, in different sizes, covering the year 1714. (Box 71, Folder 46)
  - Ferro, Carl Antonio. Letter to Baron Carlo D'Aste. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages. Signed, dated June 15, 1715. Rome. (Box 71, Folder 47)
  - Ancona... Report, unsigned, sent from Ancona, August 9, 1716, informing about the inefficiency and obsolescence of the galley ships anchored in the harbor of Ancona. Ms. 3 pages, numbered ff. 96-97. (Box 71, Folder 48)
  - Bologna, Sept...1717. A police report. Ms. 1 page. From Bologna, informing about a plot to assassinate the King of England. The assassin designate, a certain Galimberti, has been arrested and placed in jail. He was found to be in possession of a check for 10 thousand pounds, drawn upon a businessman in Venice. (Box 71, Folder 49)
  - Ristretto Diario... and 12 other newsletters. Printed, mostly in Italian. 85 pages, covering the years 1717-1719. (Box 71, Folder 50)
  - Bologna, April 15, 1719. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, numbered f. 99. A report informing that, according to a rumor, the Spaniards had landed on the Isle of Wight and occupied Portsmouth. (Box 71, Folder 51)